Nothing can be done for this chap.
我们已经救不了他了
That's strange.
这真奇怪
There's centuries between these two weapons.
这两种武器相差了好几个世纪
What's that on his jacket?
他外套上是什么东西?
Radiation detector and a gas mask.
The two things don't go together, do they?
辐射探测器和防毒面具, 这两个东西凑不到一起吧, 不是吗?
It's like finding remains of a stone age man
with a transistor radio.
这像是同时发现一具石器时代人的尸体
Playing rock music.
玩摇滚的?
A 1 ,000 year war?
持续了1000年的战争?
-Civilisation on the point of collapse.
-What?
-文明崩塌之际  -什么?
Nothing. Just theorising, that's all.
没什么 只是推理一下而已
-Come along.  -Where are we going?
-来吧  -去哪儿?
Er...
Forward.
往前走
Even the dead have a part to play.
甚至连死人都能派上用场
Propped up to make the trenches appear fully manned.
他们被支起来 让战壕里看起来像人员充足一样
-Different sort of uniform from that other chap's.
-Yes. We may have crossed the lines.
-他们和刚才那个人穿的制服不一样  -是啊 我们大概已经跨越了战线
-Same mixture of ancient and modern, though.
-Yes.
-但还是原始与先进技术混杂在一起  -是啊
That's why I think this war
has being going on for a very long time.
这就是为什么我认为 这场战争已经持续很久了
They probably started out with the most modern
equipment but no longer have the resources.
他们或许最开始配备着最先进的装备
-Have to make do.
-War of attrition, eh? Only backwards.
-只能凑合着用了 -消耗战 只能倒退
At this rate, they're going to finish up with
bows and arrows.
照这样下去 他们最终就只剩下弓箭能用了
Well, it would explain the mixture of equipment.
呃 这样就解释了装备的混杂
Psst.
-Be careful, Sarah.  -It's all right.
-Sarah 小心点  -没事的
-It's locked.  -It's pretty solid, isn't it?
-它锁住了  -还挺结实的 不是吗
Some kind of service tunnel, I suppose.
我想大概是某种作业巷道
It might even lead into the dome.
甚至可能直通到穹顶里面
Let's see where the trench leads.
我们来看看战壕通向哪里
(PROJECTILE WHISTLING)
-It's a gas shell.  -Gas!
-是个毒气弹  -毒气!
-Poison gas.  -Respirators, quick.
-有毒气体  -那有防毒面具 快戴上
Get back!
回来!
This one's alive. Get him inside.
这个人还活着 把他带进去
There's another one here.
这里还有一个
Get him inside. Quickly.
把他带进去 快
Sit down.
坐下
Thank you.
谢谢
You're not with the military, I assume?
你不是军方的 我猜?
-I'm with the science division.
-Oh, good, good.
-我是科学部的  -哦 很好很好
Then perhaps we can talk without interruption
from rifle butts.
那也许我们可以在不被枪托顶着的情况下谈谈了
That depends.
看情况吧
If you don't answer my questions,
I shall hand you back to the military.
要是你不回答我的问题 我就把你交回军方
They take a pride in loosening tongues.
他们可是以逼供能力自傲的
Now, where did you get these things?
那么 你从哪拿到这些东西的?
Oh, here and there.
哦 这儿一点那儿一点
If I didn't know better, I should have to assume
如果我不懂行的话 我就会认为
that these were made
by some intelligence on another planet.
这些东西是由其他星球的智慧生物制造的
If you didn't know better.
如果你不懂行?
It is an established scientific fact
that in the seven galaxies
而确凿的科学事实是 在七大星系中
only Skaro is capable of supporting intelligent life.
只有Skaro能够孕育出智慧生物
It is also an established scientific fact
that there are more than seven galaxies.
另一个确凿的科学事实是 宇宙中不止七大星系
-Indeed.  -Yes.
-的确  -是的
When you passed through our security scan
当你通过我们的安检扫描时
our instruments ran a complete check on your blood
我们的设备对你的血液
and chemical make-up, encephalographic patterns and so on.
还有你的化学组成 脑电波图等一系列做了全面检查
Physiological compositions,
and so if you are from another planet...
还有生理成分 所以 要是你真的来自另一个星球
-You were saying...
-There's nothing.
-你是说  -都不匹配
Nothing conforms to any known life on this planet.
你和这个星球任何的已知生物都不匹配
Apart from external appearances.
除了外貌
You can't always judge from external appearances.
你不能总是以貌取人
Who are you?
你是谁?
-Where are you from?
-It's a long story.
Then tell me.
那告诉我
Do you have any inkling of the theory
of space dimension correlated to relative time?
你是否有想过一个理论
(ALARM RINGING)
Davros wishes all members of
the Elite scientific corps
Davros希望所有科学精英小组的成员
to assemble in the main laboratory immediately.
马上到主实验室集合
Our session will have to wait.
我们的谈话要等等了
-Davros is coming.
-Your chief scientist?
-Davros要来了  -你们的首席科学家?
He's our supreme commander.
他是我们的最高指挥官
When he calls a full meeting like this,
他召开这样的全员会议
he obviously has something
of the greatest importance to tell us.
肯定是有极其重要的事情要说
-Well, I shall be delighted to meet him.
-Stand up and keep quiet.
-那好吧 我会很高兴见到他  -起立 保持安静
If I may have your attention.
全员注意
For some time
这段时间内
I have been experimenting
with the Mark III project.
我一直在进行马克三号项目试验
Details of modifications
will be distributed later, however...
随后我会分配细节的修改任务
Howerver, I am anxious
that you should see immediately
不过 我希望你们马上就能看到
the remarkable results that I have achieved.
我取得的伟大成果
And to that end
因此 我安排了这次展示
-A Dalek.  -What?
-是一个Dalek  -什么?
A Dalek, very primitive but undeniably a Dalek.
一个Dalek 非常原始 但无法否认这就是个Dalek
You're mistaken. It's a Mark III travel machine.
你错了 这是马克三号代步机器
-If you say so.  -Halt.
-随便你  -停
Turn left, move forward.
左转 前进
That's magnificent. He's perfected voice control.
太了不起了 他完善了声控
Turn right.
右转
Move forward and circle left.
前进 向左旋转
You will agree, I think,
我觉得你们会认同
that voice control represents
an enormous step forward,
声控取得了巨大的进步
however, the best is yet to come. Nyder.
但是 这还不是最厉害的地方 Nyder
Our machine is now equipped
with a weapon for self-defence.
我们的机器现在已经装备了自卫的武器
Now, I am going to turn the machine over
to total self-control.
现在我要把机器调到全自动模式
It will be entirely independent
它能实现完全的自主
of all outside influences.
不受外界影响
A living, thinking, self-supporting creature.
一个活生生 能思考 能自给的生物
DAVROS: Brilliant.
太棒了
Brilliant! It has detected the non-conformity.
太棒了 它检测到了异质性
DALEK: Aliens. I must exterminate.
外星人 我必须消灭
-Exterminate.  -No.
-消灭  -不
You dare to interfere!
你怎敢干涉!
You have the audacity to interrupt
one of my experiments.
你好大的胆子 竟敢中断我的实验
-But it would have destroyed him.
-So you think the saving of a worthless life
-但它会杀了他的  -所以你认为救这没有价值生命
more important than the progress we have made?
比我们的成就更重要?
My creature showed a natural desire,
我创造的生物有着天生的欲望
an instinct to destroy and you interceded.
有毁灭的本能 而你却替他们求情
You will be punished for this!
你会因此受到惩罚
Davros, I'm sorry.
Davros 我很抱歉
But I believe these prisoners,
they could be extremely valuable.
但我相信 这些犯人 也许会很有用
By all means, when I finish my questions,
let the machine do what it likes with them but...
等我审问完毕 随这机器做对他们想做什么都行
I do need to interrogate them further.
但是 我真的需要进一步审讯他们
You will be punished for insubordination.
你会为以下犯上而受到惩罚的
In the meantime, you may question the prisoners
until first light.
在这期间 你可以审问这些犯人 直到日出
After that, they will be used to resume
the experiment.
在那之后 他们会被用来继续我的实验
This meeting is ended.
会议结束
-Thank you, I am obliged to you.
-I was merely doing my duty.
-谢谢 我很感激  -我只是尽我的职责罢了
I believe that you have knowledge
which could be of the greatest assistance to us.
我相信你拥有的知识 能帮上我们大忙
But if you don't cooperate,
但要是你不合作
then it is certain that Davros will use you
as an experiment
那么Davros肯定会在几个小时之内
with his machine in a few hours' time.
拿你们给他的机器做实验
The prisoners are to be taken to the cells,
you can continue questioning them there.
把犯人押送到囚室里 你可以在那继续审讯他们
Davros orders it.
Davros下的命令
-You all right?  -Looks like I might be.
-你还好吧?  -看样子还好
What happened?
怎么了
They took down reams of notes.
他们记了非常多的笔记
Every bit of scientific gobbledegook
I could think of.
记下了我能想到的每一个晦涩的科学名词
Technical jargon that even I didn't understand.
还有一些连我也不懂的科技术语
-That'll keep their experts tied up for weeks.
-Yes.
-这样就能把他们的专家拖上几周  -是啊
And I learnt a great deal more from them
than they did from me.
我还了解到了好多信息 比他们从我这里得到的还多
-About this bunker?
-Yes.
-关于这个掩体?  -是啊
-It is underground, isn't it?
-Yes, bomb-proof.
-它位于地下 对吧  -嗯 而且防炸弹
Impregnable from attack from the outside and
about three or four miles from the Kaled dome.
从外部无法攻破 离Kaled穹顶有三四英里远
What are they doing down here?
他们在这下面做什么?
Years ago, the Kaled government
decided to form an elite group.
多年前 Kaled政府决定组织一个精英小组
The best scientific brains in every field.
请来各领域最厉害的科学家
-A sort of think tank.  -Yes.
-有点像智囊团  -对
But over the years the Elite has become
more and more powerful
但是多年以来精英小组的势力
and now they can demand whatever they like.
现在他们可以随心所欲了
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
-Open up.
-Perhaps this is the tea.
-开门  -也许茶送来了
There's no need to wait, I am armed.
不用等了 我有武器的
I'm sorry if they hurt you.
如果他们伤到你了 我很抱歉
I lack the courage to interfere.
我不敢妨碍他们
But you did save me from becoming
the very first victim of a Dalek. Thank you.
但你确实救了我 让我不至于变成第一个被Dalek杀死的受害者 谢谢你
Yes, now you used that word earlier.
It had never been heard before.
是啊 你之前也用过那个词 之前从来没有人听过这个词
And yet only an hour ago,
Davros announced that henceforth
不过一个小时以前 Davros宣布
his Mark III travel machine would be
referred to as a Dalek.
从今往后他的马克三号代步机器 要被称为Dalek
Now how could you have known that?
你怎么可能早就知道?
Well, I have an advantage in terms of time.
在时间方面我有优势
You see, we've come here at this time
because of...
你看 我们在这个时候来这里是因为
futue concert about the development of the Dalek.
我们对Dalek的未来发展很担忧
I think you're concerned, too, aren't you?
我想你也有些担忧 对吧
(WHISPERING) I think he's going to bite.
我想他要上钩了
Yes, I am concerned and there are a few others
who think the same as I.
是啊 我确实很担忧
-But we're powerless.
-Then let us help you.
-但我们没有权力  -那就让我们帮你们吧
You see, we believe that
你看 我们认为
Davros has changed the direction of our research
into something which is...
Davros已经改变了我们的研究方向 使其变得
immoral, evil.
不道德 很邪恶
You see, the Elite was formed
你看 精英小组成立的初衷
to produce weapons that would end this war.
是想生产出能结束战争的武器
We soon saw that this was futile
and changed the direction of our research into...
我们很快就发现这是徒劳的 并将研究方向转为
into the survival of our race.
拯救我们的种族
But our chemical weapons had already
started to produce genetic mutations.
但我们的化学武器已经 开始导致基因变异了
And the mutations were banished
out into the wastelands.
然后你们把变异的人驱逐到荒地上
-Yes.  -The mutos.
-对  -就是那些变异人
Now Davros, he believed that there was
no way to reverse this trend
现在 Davros认为 这种趋势无法逆转
and so he started experiments
所以他开始做实验
to establish our final mutational form.
来造出我们的最终变异形式
He took living cells,
他取出活细胞
treated them with chemicals
用化学药物培养
and produced the ultimate creature.
然后产生了终极生物
Come with me.
跟我来
Now this is what the Kaleds will become.
这就是Kaled人最后会变成的样子
(GROWLING)
That is our future.
那就是我们的未来
Go on, Ronson.
接着说 Ronson
Well, knowing our ultimate form,
Davros had to devise a travel machine.
知道了我们的终极形态之后 Davros就要设计一种代步机器
-The Dalek.
-Now he's trying to change that into a weapon.
-Dalek  -现在 他在尝试把它变成一种武器
And he's succeeding.
而且他就要成功了
He's created a monster, utterly devoid of conscience.
他发明的是一种怪物 毫无良知
-And you want to stop him?
-Well, I must.
-所以你想要阻止他?  -是 我必须这么做
There are a few in the Kaled government
who still have the power to act.
Kaled政府里还是有一些人
If they knew the truth,
they would end Davros' power,
如果他们知道了真相
close down this bunker, finish the only...
把这个掩体关停 终结掉那个仅有的...
Then go to them, Ronson, go to them.
那就去找他们啊 Ronson 去找他们
But I'm not allowed in the city.
Security here is absolute.
但是我是不能进城的 这里的安保非常严格
Then help us to escape. Give us the names
of the men who have the power.
那就帮我们逃出去 把掌权者们的名字告诉我们
Could you get us out of here?
你能带我们离开这里吗
There is a way.
倒是有一条出路
Through one of the secondary ducts
in the ventilation system
经过通风系统的一条辅助管道
that leads to a cave at the edge of the wasteland.
就可以通往荒地边缘的一个洞穴
-Well?  -The entrance is barred.
-嗯?  -你的意思是?
And there's something else.
而且还有别的麻烦
Davros' early experiments were with animals.
Davros早期的实验用的都是动物
Some of the things that he created were horrific.
他创造的一些东西特别的恐怖
And they're still alive.
而它们都还活着
And I have an uneasy feeling
you're going to tell me they're in that cave.
我有一种不祥的预感
These are the people you should try to contact.
这些是你要尝试联系的人
Righto.
好的
Look, if anything at all should happen...
我说 如果发生了任何事...
Don't worry, we won't let it fall into wrong hands.
别担心 我们不会让它落入坏人之手
I've just had word
from one of our supporters in the dome.
我刚收到穹顶内一位支持者发来的消息
Councillor Mogran has called a secret meeting.
Mogran议员召开了一个秘密会议
The only councillors invited are known opponents
of the work we are doing here in the bunker.
被邀请到的议员都是反对我们在掩体里进行实验的
I want a full report
on everything that was discussed.
我需要一份会议讨论内容的完整报告
I don't care how you get the information, get it.
我不关心你怎么搞到消息 给我弄来
I think we need not be too concerned.
我认为我们无需太过担心
Many times in the last 50 years, factions
of the government have tried to interfere
在过去的五十年里 政府内的反对派曾多次企图干涉我的实验
with my research here, they have failed.
但最终他们都失败了
They will fail again.
他们会再次失败的
There's something else. The two prisoners in
Ronson's charge, they've been seen at the dome.
还有别的情况 Ronson负责的那两个犯人
-They are at the meeting.
-Impossible!
-他们参加了会议  -不可能!
-There is no escape from here.
-I've checked their cells. They are missing.
这里根本逃不出去 我检查了他们的牢房 他们失踪了
Find out how they escaped
and report to me immediately.
查出他们究竟是怎么逃跑的 然后立即向我汇报
-What action shall I take concerning Ronson?
-For the moment, none.
-我该如何处理Ronson  -目前先别打草惊蛇
I will deal with him in my own way.
我自有办法处理他
-That was a very impressive speech, Doctor.
-Yes, it was meant to be.
-你讲的内容非常发人深省 博士  -是呀 我本意如此
Let's hope it's convinced them.
但愿那些话能够说服他们吧
Yes, let's hope so, Harry.
Sometimes words aren't enough.
没错 我们希望如此吧 Harry 有时候言语是不够的
Well, they seem to have reached a decision.
他们好像是做了决定了
I'm afraid, Doctor, the councillors could not
agree to halt all experimentation at the bunker.
我很抱歉 博士 那些议员不同意停止掩体里进行的所有实验
-The councillors are fools.
-Let me finish, please.
-这些议员是蠢货  -请让我把话说完好吗
It has been agreed that an independent tribunal
大家一致同意将由一个独立法庭
will investigate all work
that is being done at the bunker.
专门来调查掩体里进行的所有工作
But that could take months.
但那需要几个月的时间
Davros already has several
prototype Daleks ready for action.
Davros已经造出好几台Dalek样机 准备行动了
It has also been agreed that,
pending the investigation,
大家也达成一致 在调查期间
Davros' experiments will be suspended.
Davros的实验将被暂停
It is less than I'd hoped for.
这可没有达到我的预期
And I promise you, Doctor,
if your allegations are borne out,
我向你保证 博士 如果你声称的那些得到了证实
-all work at the bunker will be closed down.
-Thank you.
-掩体里的一切实验都将被关停  -谢谢
And now I must go with my committee
and inform Davros of our decision.
现在我要和我的委员会 一起去告诉Davros我们的决定
I think it's high time
we looked for Sarah, don't you?
现在我们该去找Sarah了 对吧?
-The one you left behind in the wastelands?
-Yes, you have some news of her?
-那个被你们留在荒地的人?  -是的 你有她的消息吗?
I can't be certain, you understand?
我不是很确定 你们明白吗?
But our agents inside the Thal dome
report a newly arrived girl prisoner
但我们安插在Thal穹顶里的特工 汇报说那边来了一个女犯人
who led an attempted break-out.
Gave the Thals quite a bit of trouble.
领导了一次越狱 没成功 但给Thal人添了不少麻烦
-That'll be her.
-In the Thal dome, you say?
-那就是她了  -你是说在Thal穹顶里吗?
The Thals are using prisoners
to load their last great rocket.
Thal人让囚犯填装他们的终极大火箭
-Rocket?
-They think they'll win the war with it.
-火箭?  -他们认为能靠它赢得战争
What they don't know is that
no matter how powerful their rocket,
他们不知道的是 无论他们的火箭有多厉害
it cannot penetrate our protective dome.
都不能穿透我们的保护穹顶
Only a matter of months ago,
Davros perfected a new substance
就在几个月前 Davros完善了一种新物质
which has the strength
of 30-foot thick reinforced concrete.
能达到三十英尺厚的加强混凝土的强度
Yes, well, never mind about that.
Could you help us to find Sarah?
好吧 别管那个了 你能帮我们找到Sarah吗
One of my agents could lead you
into the service shaft underneath the Thal city.
我的一个特工可以带你们到Thal城下方的维护竖井
-But after that, you're strictly on your own.
-Fair enough.
-但在那之后 你们就全靠自己了  -好吧
Right, I'll give you a map
showing how to reach the rocket silo area.
好的 我会给你们一份地图
Thank you.
谢谢你
An investigation? But of course, Mogran.
调查? 当然可以 Mogran
I welcome any inquiry into our work here.
I think the idea is an excellent one.
我欢迎对我们工作的任何调查 我觉得这个主意真不错
There's one thing more.
Until the inquiry, all work is to be suspended.
还有件事 在调查时 要暂停所有的工作
If that is your wish, then naturally I will obey.
如果你希望这样 那我自然会服从
It will take some time
to close down certain pieces of equipment.
不过某些设备 需要一定时间才能关闭
Shall we say 24 hours?
能给24小时吗
-Twelve.
-It will be difficult but it will be done.
-12小时  -有点难 但也能做到
The members of the tribunal
will arrive in that time.
到那时 会有独立法庭的成员过来
We cannot allow this investigation!
我们不能让调查进行
They cannot fail to see the dangers
to themselves in the Dalek project.
他们不可能看不出 Dalek项目中他们自身所处的危险
Calm yourself, Nyder.
Nyder 冷静一点
-There will be no investigation.
-But you can't stop it now.
-不会有调查的  -但你现在无法阻止啊
I can and will!
我可以 并且会阻止的
The Council has signed the death warrant
of the whole of the Kaled people.
议会这是为所有Kaled人 签下了死刑令
Only we, the Elite, we and the Daleks will go on.
只有我们 精英小组 我们和Dalek会存活下去
The whole of the Kaled people?
You would go that far?
所有Kaled人? 你会做得那么绝?
Did you ever doubt it?
你怀疑过?
No.
没有
There is much to do.
还有很多事情要做
I want the genetically conditioned creatures
installed in the machines immediately.
我要把基因改造生物立即放进机器里
-20 of them.
-20?
-要20个  -20个?
-They are our troops in this battle for survival.
-But they are still very erratic, unstable.
-他们是我们这场生存之战中的军队  -但他们还很不稳定
They will not be allowed self-control.
我不会允许他们自主控制的
I will prepare a computer program
that will limit their actions.
我会编一个计算机程序来限制他们的行动
After that, we are going on a journey.
在那之后 我们就出一趟门
-You think they believed you?
-It is unimportant.
-你觉得他们信任你吗  -这不重要
They are hungry for victory.
他们迫切地渴望胜利
They will use the formula and fire their rocket
no matter what they believe my motives to be.
他们会利用配方 发射他们的火箭 不管他们认为我的动机是什么
And when they do, Nyder, when they do...
等他们行动时 Nyder 等他们行动时...
I've given orders that a barrage of shells/?
我下了命令 尽快开始密集发射
containing the formula should begin as soon as possible.
一批填充了那种化学物质的炮弹
The rocket launch can begin immediately.
火箭发射可以立即开始
And now I'll arrange
your safe escort out of the city.
现在我安排人护送你们安全出城
Doctor, somehow we've got to warn Mogran
and the other Kaled leaders.
博士 我们必须想办法警告Morgan
Yes, and we haven't found Sarah yet. Come on.
是的 而且我们还没找到Sarah 快走
Excuse me, can you help me? I'm a spy.
打扰下 能帮帮我吗 我是个间谍
Their suits, Harry.
他们的制服 Harry
-Harry! Doc...
-You all right, Sarah?
-Harry 博...  -你还好吗 Sarah
Oh! I am now. Listen, we've got to get out of here.
哦 现在好了 听着 我们必须离开这里
-The Thals are going to launch this rocket...
-Yes, yes. I know. Listen.
-Thal人准备发射这火箭  -我知道 听着
I want you and Harry to go back
to the Kaled dome. Harry knows the way.
我要你和Harry回Kaled穹顶里去 Harry知道怎么走
Tell them all we know. There's a chance
if they launch an all-out offensive,
把掌握的一切都告诉他们 如果他们发起全面进攻 或许还有机会
-I might be able to stop the rocket.
-What are you going to do?
-我也许能阻止火箭发射  -你要怎么做
-Try to sabotage it, or at least delay it. Off you go.
-Right.
-尽量破坏它 至少要拖延一段时间 你们走吧  -好吧
-Good luck.  -Sevrin, you come with us.
-好运  -Sevrin 你跟我们走
I sent Harry and Sarah in there.
是我叫Harry和Sarah去那里面的
Switch it off.
关上它
We will avenge the annihilation of our people
with a retaliation so massive,
我们要报此灭族之仇 用最有力最无情的手段报复
so merciless that it will live in history.
让它永载史册
Let the vengeance begin
with the death of the arch traitor,
我们的复仇就从杀了头号叛徒
the Thal spy Ronson!
Thal间谍Ronson开始吧
No! Davros!
不要! Davros!
Exterminate!
消灭
-Exterminate!  -No!
-消灭  -不
No!
不
Today the Kaled race is ended,
consumed in a fire of war,
今天Kaled族在战火中终结了
but from its ashes will rise a new race,
但从灰烬之中 一个新的种族将会崛起
the supreme creature,
the ultimate conqueror of the universe,
一种睥睨万物的生灵 宇宙的终极征服者
the Dalek!
Dalek!
-Did you have friends in the Kaled city?
-Yes.
-你在Kaled城里有朋友吗  -是的
Two people very dear to me.
两个对我来说很重要的人
I sent them into that holocaust.
是我让他们卷进这场灾难
What will you do now?
你现在要做什么呢
Start again.
重新开始
Try and find a way to complete what I set out to do
尽力想办法完成我来这里该做的事
and stop the development of the Daleks.
阻止Dalek进一步发展
-Daleks?  -Yes.
-Dalek?  -是啊
Machine creatures that Davros is developing, monsters.
Davros正在研发的一种机器生物 一种怪物
Davros? No, you're wrong.
Davros? 不对 你错了
It was he who told us
how to destroy the Kaled dome.
正是他告诉我们怎么摧毁Kaled穹顶的
-His only interest is in achieving peace.
-Let me tell you something.
-他只想要得到和平  -告诉你吧
The Kaled government was on the point
of stopping Davros' experiments.
那时候Kaled政府 正要暂停Davros的实验
And rather than let that happen,
he helped you to destroy his own race.
为了不让那样的事发生 他帮助你们消灭了他自己的种族
You'll never convince my people of that.
Davros is a hero.
我的族人永远不会相信的 Davros是个英雄
Yes, for how long I wonder.
好吧 那也长不了了
I must go.
我得走了
Under the general amnesty,
you're free to leave whenever you want.
因为大赦令 你自由了 想什么时候离开都行
Thank you.
谢谢你了
-Well?
-The Daleks are in position.
-说吧  -Dalek已就位
They will act on your command.
他们会依你的命令行动
I see no reason to delay any longer.
没有再拖延的理由了
(PEOPLE CHEERING)
Exterminate!
消灭
(YELLING)
-What are they?  -Keep back.
-他们是什么?  -到后面去
Get out of sight.
别让他们看见
We've got to get out of the Thal dome.
我们得逃出Thal穹顶
-Are those the Daleks?
-Out into the wastelands. Do you know a way?
-这些就是Dalek?  -到外面荒地去 你知道怎么走吗?
Good. Yes, they are the Daleks.
Come on, lead the way.
好的 没错 他们就是Dalek 来吧 带路
DALEKS: (IN THE DISTANCE) Exterminate!
Exterminate!
消灭
Oh, there was no need to go that far.
我们没必要跑那么远
When our leaders saw they were beaten,
they should've surrendered.
如果我们的领导者意识到他们已经失败
Perhaps they did.
也许他们已经投降了
But Daleks accept no terms,
但是Dalek不会讨价还价
they're programmed to wipe the Thals
from the face of this planet.
But there must be some who'll escape.
Some survivors.
但一定有人会逃出去的 会有幸存者的
A few perhaps.
也许会有一些
But they need to be grouped together into
some kind of fighting force to strike the bunker.
但是 我们需要把他们聚在一起 组成一支战队来进攻掩体
-What?
-Destroy Davros and you destroy the Daleks.
-什么?  -杀了Davros 你就消灭Daleks
-What chance do we have against them?
-It's your only chance.
-我们能有什么机会打赢他们呢?  -这是你们唯一的机会了
Will you do it?
你愿意去吗?
Yes.
愿意
Good girl. I'm going to try
and get back into the bunker.
好姑娘 我会试着回到掩体里去
-Alone?  -Good luck.
-一个人?  -好运
Exterminate!
消灭
SARAH: All right?
HARRY: Yes.
-没事吧?  -没事
Doctor?
博士?
-Harry!  -Hello.
-Harry!  -你好
-Sarah! I can hardly believe it.
-What's the matter with you?
-Sarah! 难以置信  -你怎么了?
I thought you were in the Kaled dome
when it was hit.
我以为Kaled穹顶被击中时你们在里面
-We didn't get there.  -No.
-我们没能到那里  -不
Halfway across the wastelands
we were attacked by a band of mutos.
我们在穿过荒地的半路上 就被一队变异人袭击了
And that's when the rocket was launched.
就在那时火箭发射了
-And then when the Kaled dome exploded...
-The mutos just ran for their lives.
-当Kaled穹顶爆炸时  -那些变异人为了保命就逃了
Of course, I knew you'd try and get back
into the bunker through the cave.
当然 我知道你会试着穿过洞穴回到掩体里去
You were absolutely right, Harry.
It's vital we go back into the bunker.
你猜得很对 Harry 我们一定要回到掩体里去
-Why?
-Because they took the time ring.
-为什么?  -因为他们拿走了时间手环
The bracelet that the Time Lord gave me
is our lifeline.
时间领主给我的手环是我们的救生索
Without it we can never escape from this planet.
没了它我们就逃不出这个星球了
Sevrin, would you do something for us,
something important?
Sevrin 你能帮我们做些事情么 重要的事情
Over in the Kaled trenches,
there's a Thal, a girl named Bettan.
在Kaled战壕里面 有个Thal人 一个叫Bettan的姑娘
She's trying to form a resistance group.
她在努力组织一支反抗队伍
Join her with as many of your own people
as you can get.
尽可能多地带你们的人加入她
Their idea is to knock out the bunker.
他们打算攻破掩体
Do you think they'll get away with it?
你觉得他们能成功么
It'll keep the Elite's troops occupied
while I try to find a weakness of the Daleks.
这能让精英小队的军队无暇他顾
Good luck, Doctor.
祝你好运 博士
Sevrin, thank you.
Sevrin 谢谢你
(GROWLING)
Who's that?
谁在哪儿
Just one of Davros' experiments.
只是Davros的一个试验品
We better stick close together.
我们最好待在一起
HARRY: You're not scared, are you?
SARAH: Of course not.
-你不害怕吧?  -当然不怕
I am.
我有点儿
Listen, I've been down tunnels before
and I've just had a rather nasty thought.
听着 我以前也钻过隧道
-Really?  -Yes.
-真的么  -没错
Suppose something's waiting for us in there.
试想一下有东西在那一头等着我们
That is nasty.
确实很糟糕
Better not tell Harry, he's gone first.
最好别告诉Harry 他走在第一个
Welcome back.
欢迎回来
You were right, Sarah,
about there being something nasty waiting for us.
你是对的 Sarah 真有一些糟糕的东西在等着我们
I have read the initial reports
of your interrogation.
我看过对你审讯的原始记录
The suggestion that you have travelled
through space and time
电脑分析彻底驳回了
was utterly dismissed by the computer analysis.
你在时间和空间旅行的说法
I imagine it had never been programmed for such a concept.
我想是计算机从未被编程设定过这种概念吧
Precisely.
没错
I, however, I am perhaps more flexible.
然而 我也许更能变通
Though the power of such travel
is beyond my scientific comprehension,
尽管这种旅行 在科学层面上超越了我的理解能力
it is not beyond my imagination.
但没有超乎我的想象
Why did you come here?
你为什么来这里
-To stop the development of the Daleks.
-Why?
-阻止Dalek的进化  -为什么
Because having lived
in what you would call the future,
我曾生活在对你而言还是未来的时候
I have seen the carnage
and destruction they have caused.
我目睹了他们造成的屠杀和毁灭
Then my Daleks do go on. They do survive.
所以说我的Dalek确实继续存在着 他们活下来了
Yes. As weapons of hate and machines of war.
是的 作为仇恨的武器 战争的机器
-Fascinating.
-But there's still time to change all that.
-好极了  -但还有机会改变这一切
Why not make them a force for good
throughout the universe?
为什么不将他们创造成宇宙中正义的力量呢
-I could do it.
-Then do it.
-我也可以这么做  -那就去做啊
Be remembered for that.
并以此名垂青史
You have seen my Daleks in battle?
你见过我的Dalek参战?
Many times. I've fought against them.
很多次 我曾与他们交战
And do they win? Do they always win?
他们赢了吗 他们是不是总是能胜利?
Not always. They have been defeated.
不是总是 他们被打败过
But never utterly defeated.
但从未被彻底打败过
The Dalek menace always remains.
Dalek的威胁一直都存在
If, as you say, they become
the supreme creatures of war,
若是如你所说 他们成了为战争而生的终极造物
how can they lose? How can they fail?
那他们怎么能输 他们怎么能失败
Misfortune, lack of information,
sometimes overwhelming opposition.
不走运 缺乏信息 有时是敌方力量过于强大
Yes, but tell me, how do the Daleks fail?
是的 但告诉我 Dalek是怎么败的
No, Davros,
不 Davros
that is a question that the future must keep secret.
这个问题 是未来必须保守的秘密
What mistakes do they make?
他们会犯些什么错
-You will tell me!  -No.
-告诉我  -不
-You will tell me!  -No, I will not!
-告诉我  -不 不行
Nyder.
Nyder
You will tell me because you have a weakness
你会说的 因为你有一处弱点
that I have totally eliminated
from the minds of the Daleks
我已把它彻底从Dalek的思维中消除了
so they will always be superior.
所以他们永远处于优势地位
A weakness that will make you
give me the knowledge to change the future.
这个弱点会迫使你 给我那些信息去改变未来
You are afflicted with a conscience.
你会受到良知的折磨
Nyder.
Nyder
Let me tell you what is going to happen.
让我来告诉你会发生什么
You will answer my questions.
You will answer them carefully and precisely.
你回答我的问题 你仔细地 准确地回答我的问题
The instruments to which you are wired
are particularly sensitive.
连在你身上的那些仪器 极其敏感
They will detect instantly any attempt to lie.
能立刻察觉到任何尝试说谎的行为
-And if I do lie?
-If you lie, your friends will suffer.
-如果我确实说谎了呢  -如果你说谎了 你的朋友会受苦
I can create in their bodies
我能对他们的身体施加
all the torments and agonies ever known.
世上所知的全部折磨与痛苦
(BEEPING INTENSIFIES)
Don't tell him, Doctor.
别告诉他 博士
Now, you will tell me the reason
for every Dalek defeat.
现在 告诉我Dalek每次失败的原因
With that knowledge, I will program them.
有了这些信息 我会给他们编程
With that knowledge, they will know their errors
and how to avoid them.
有了这些信息 他们会知道自己的错误 知道怎样避免
With that knowledge, there will be no defeats!
有了这些信息 他们将百战百胜
We will begin!
开始
Davros...
Davros
if I tell you what you want to know,
I betray millions of people in the future.
如果我告诉你你想知道的这些 我就背叛了千千万万未来的人们
-I can't do that.  -But you can!
-我不能这样做  -你能
You will tell me!
你会说的
Doctor, please, don't tell... Doctor!
博士 拜托 别告诉... 博士!
All right, all right!
好了好了
Just leave them alone.
放过他们吧
Dalek invasion of the Earth in the year 2000 was foiled
在2000年 Dalek在入侵地球时被挫败
because of an attempt by the Daleks
to mine the core of the planet.
因为他们试图钻探地核
-The magnetic properties of the Earth...
-Mars...
-地磁极...  -火星...
the Daleks were defeated by a virus that
Dalek败于一种
attacked the insulation on the cables
in their electrical systems.
能攻击他们电路系统上电线绝缘层的病毒
...in the space year 1 7,000,
在宇宙历17000年
was halted by the intervention
of a fleet of war rockets
从重核子星发射的战争火箭舰队
from the planet Hyperon.
制止了他们
The rockets were made of a metal
制造火箭的金属
that was completely resistant to Dalek firepower.
完全可以抵御Dalek的火力
The Dalek Task Force was completely destroyed.
Dalek特别小组全部被歼灭
It seems an opportune moment
to end this session. Nyder.
这一阶段的审讯正好结束 Nyder
Release the prisoners.
Take them to the detention area.
给犯人松绑  把他们带到拘留区
Interrogation will continue later.
And I must thank you, Doctor.
审讯一会儿再继续 我得谢谢你 博士
What you have told me will be invaluable.
你说的这些是无价之宝
All the information, this foreknowledge,
所有这些信息 这些预告式信息
will be programmed into the Dalek memory banks.
Take them away.
都会编程到Dalek的记忆库里 把他们带走
Doctor, stay a moment.
博士 先留步
Sit down.
坐下
Let us talk together now,
not as prisoner and captor,
我们谈谈吧 不是以犯人和逮捕者的身份
but as men of science.
而是以科学家的身份
There is so much I wish to know.
我想知道的太多了
-Nyder, take charge of the tape.
-Immediately, Davros.
-Nyder 你保管好录音带  -马上 Davros
It will be your responsibility
and remember, it is priceless.
这将是你的职责 你记住了 这是无价之宝
Its value beyond computation.
它的价值无法估量
-Thank you.  -Who are you?
-谢谢  -你是谁
-My name's Gharman.  -Gharman?
-我叫Gharman  -Gharman?
Until a few hours ago,
I was head of the Military Elite Scientific Corps.
几小时以前 我还是军方精英小组科学部的负责人
And now you're a prisoner like us? What happened?
现在你和我们一样是犯人了?
Wait.
你等等
I was trying to organise a movement against Davros.
我试图组织一场反对Davros的运动
He found out.
被他发现了
Now, what's happening out there?
现在外面情况如何
Has there been any attempt
to take away control from Davros?
有没有人试过夺Davros的权?
Not that we know of.
据我们所知没有
Halt! State your business.
站住 说明来意
I wish to question the prisoners.
我要审问犯人
Nobody is allowed to communicate with the prisoners
任何人都不得与犯人交谈
unless they have a pass signed by Davros.
除非有Davros签的许可证
Stay where you are!
站着别动
I...seem to have mislaid it.
我好像把它落在哪儿了
I'll come back later.
我过一会再来
Now future errors will be eradicated.
未来的错误将被剔除
Defeats will become victories.
失败将变成胜利
You have changed
the future of the universe, Doctor.
你改变了整个宇宙的未来 博士
I have betrayed the future.
我背叛了未来
Davros, for the last time,
consider what you're doing.
Davros 最后一次 再想想你在做的事情
Stop the development of the Daleks.
不要再研发Dalek了
Impossible. It is beyond my control.
不可能的 这我已经无法控制了
The workshops are already fully automated
to produce the Dalek machines.
工厂已经全面自动化生产Dalek机器了
It's not the machines.
It's the minds of the creatures inside them.
我说的不是那些机器 而是里面那些生物的心智
Minds that you created. They are totally evil.
你创造出来的心智 他们是绝对邪恶的
Evil? No.
邪恶? 不
No, I will not accept that.
不 我不同意
They are conditioned simply to survive.
他们被培养成这样 只是为了生存
They can survive only by becoming
the dominant species.
他们只有成为统领一切的物种才能生存
When all other life forms are suppressed,
当其他物种被压制
when the Daleks are the supreme rulers
of the universe,
Dalek成为宇宙最高统治者的时候
then you will have peace.
天下就太平了
Wars will end.
战争就结束了
They are the power not of evil, but of good!
他们不是邪恶力量 而是正义力量!
Davros, if you had created a virus in your laboratory,
Davros 如果你在实验室研制出一种病毒
something contagious and infectious
that killed on contact,
一种会蔓延 易传染 接触即可致命的病毒
a virus that would destroy all other forms of life,
一种能够消灭任何其他形式生命体的病毒
would you allow its use?
你会批准使用它么
-It is an interesting conjecture.
-Would you do it?
-这是个很有趣的设想  -你会这样做么
The only living thing,
唯一存活的生命体
a microscopic organism,
一种微小的生物
reigning supreme.
成为最高主宰
-A fascinating idea.  -But would you do it?
-真是个绝妙的想法  -但你会不会这样做
Yes.
会
当然
To hold in my hand
握于我手中
a capsule that contains such power,
一粒小小胶囊 容括如此威力
to know that life and death
on such a scale was my choice.
无数生死只系我一念之间
To know that the tiny pressure on my thumb,
只需我拇指的一点点压力
enough to break the glass, would end everything.
就足以压碎玻璃 终结一切
Yes.
会的
I would do it.
我会这么做的
That power would set me up above the gods.
那种权力将把我置于神灵之上
And through the Daleks, I shall have that power!
通过Dalek 我将获得那种权力
-Release me.  -No, Davros.
-放开我  -不 Davros
-Don't touch that switch.  -Why not?
-别碰那个开关  -为什么不呢
It controls my life support systems.
它控制着我的生命维持系统
I could not survive 30 seconds without them.
没有它们我连30秒都活不了
Order the destruction of the incubator section.
那就下令摧毁培育部门
Destroy the Daleks? Never.
摧毁Dalek? 绝不
(ALARM BEEPING)
I mean it, Davros.
我是认真的 Davros
Next time I press that switch, it stays pressed.
Now give the order!
下次我摁下按钮 就不会放开了 现在下令吧
Even if I do this, there will be no escape for you.
即是我这样做了 你也无法逃脱
I'll take that chance. Now give the order.
我宁愿冒这个风险 现在快下令
Press the communicator switch.
拨开通讯开关
This is Davros.
我是Davros
Elite unit 7 will go to the incubator room.
精英第七小组立即前往培育室
All survival maintenance systems
are to be closed down.
关闭所有生命维持系统
The Dalek creatures are to be destroyed.
毁灭所有Dalek生物
Tell them the order cannot be countermanded.
告诉他们命令不能被撤销
This order cannot...
这条命令不能...
This is Davros. This is Davros.
我是Davros 我是Davros
My last order is cancelled. Repeat, cancelled.
我的上一条命令撤销 重复一次 撤销
No action is to be taken.
不要执行命令
What do you want done with this?
你想怎么处理他
For the moment, he must be kept alive.
目前 他必须活着
He has knowledge that is vital to our future.
他掌握的信息对我们的未来至关重要
And I will drain
every last detail of it from his mind.
我会从他的大脑里榨出一切关于未来的细节
And then,
在那之后
he will learn the true meaning of pain.
他会知道什么是真正的痛苦
I will take him to the detention room.
我会把他带到拘留室
The dissidents. What progress are they making?
那些反对者 他们的行动有什么进展
Feeling against you is rising.
对你的不满情绪正在上升
Many of the scientific corps
are openly speaking against you.
许多科学部成员都公开抨击你
Even some of the military are joining them.
甚至一些军队里的人也加入了他们
As I expected.
在我意料之中
-They will take action soon?
-Almost certainly.
They outnumber those of us who are loyal.
他们的数量大于忠于我们的人
Davros, why don't you let me take
a squad of Elite men I can trust?
Davros 你为什么不让我
In an hour, I could wipe out their leaders.
不出一个小时 我就能彻底摧毁他们的领导层
You think like a soldier, Nyder.
你的思考方式像一个士兵 Nyder
Rebellion is an idea in the mind.
叛乱只是大脑中的一个想法
Suppress it and it hides away and festers.
抑制它 它就会隐藏起来 不断溃烂
No. My way is best.
不 我的方法才是最好的
As you wish.
听您的
On your feet!
站起来
Open up.
Not exactly as planned, Sarah.
这跟计划有些出入啊 Sarah
Doctor.
博士
-He's a bit groggy but he'll be all right.
-Come on, Kavell, we've a lot to do.
-他有些晕 但他会没事的 -来吧 Kavell 我们还有很多事要做
What about the guards?
Suppose they won't come over to our side?
那些警卫怎么办 要是他们不愿意加入我们这边怎么办?
They'll be disarmed and held in custody
until we've presented our ultimatum to Davros.
那就把他们缴械监禁起来 直到我们向Davros提出最后通牒
No, wait, wait. Davros knows what you're planning.
别 等等 Davros知道你们在计划些什么
I heard him talking to Nyder.
我听到了他和Nyder的对话
If he knows,
why hasn't he taken action against us?
如果他知道了 为什么不采取行动制止我们
Perhaps because he knows it's futile.
也许是因为他知道那是徒劳的
-There are too many of us.
-No, no, it's not that.
-他们寡不敌众  -不 不是这样的
I don't know what he's got prepared for you
but believe me, he's ready.
我不知道他准备怎么对付你们 但相信我 他已经准备好了
Even so, there'll still be too many for him.
即使这样 我们人多 他招架不住的
Just be careful. Be careful.
务必小心 一定要小心
I think we can take care of things.
Thanks for the warning.
我们自己能处理这些事情 谢谢你的提醒
-No point in telling you to rest, I suppose.
-No, there isn't.
-我让你休息一下你也不会听的吧  -没错
We've got to recover that time ring.
我们必须拿回时间手环
Because without it, we'll never
get off this planet. But where is it?
因为没有它 我们就无法离开这个星球 但它在哪儿呢
It's on the desk in the main laboratory.
在主实验室的桌子上
And there's that tape recording that Nyder took.
We've got to get it back at all costs.
还有Nyder拿去的那盘磁带 我们无论如何都要把它拿回来
It would make the Daleks invincible. Come on.
它能使Dalek变得不可战胜 走吧
Davros, they're taking over. We must act quickly.
Davros 他们在渐渐控制局面 我们必须快点行动
In another hour, they could be totally in control.
再过一个小时 他们就能掌控全局了
Do you hear me, Davros?
你听到了吗 Davros?
I have a dozen crack men hiding in section 9.
我有一些训练有素的手下埋伏在9区
Let me order them into action.
让我命令他们采取行动
-Davros?  -I hear you.
-Davros?  -我听见了
Then what are we going to do?
那我们接下来要怎么办?
I want you to find their leaders
and hand over your weapons to them.
我希望你找到他们的领头人
Surrender?
投降?
Order all members of the Elite guards
still at liberty to do the same.
下令让所有未被捕的精英小组警卫也这么做
Do you know what you're saying?
你知道你在说什么吗?
I know precisely what I am saying.
我所说的话我自己当然清楚
Now, I will command and you will obey!
现在 我下令 你遵命
You will do as I order!
你要按我的命令行事!
You will inform the rebel leaders
that I have given these orders to avoid bloodshed.
告诉那些反抗者领头人 我的命令是为了避免流血牺牲
Tell them I submit
and will listen to their demands.
告诉他们 我投降 并会听他们的要求
-That is all.
-Then we are admitting that we're beaten.
-就这些  -我们这是要承认被打败了
That is what they will believe.
他们会这么相信而已
You mean that...
你的意思是
You and they will find out exactly what I mean
all in good time.
你和他们 都会在时机成熟时 明白我的意思
Now carry out my orders.
现在执行我的命令
(ELECTRONIC BUZZING)
(WHISPERING) Useful.
会有用的
Ah.
啊
This is something rather more useful.
这东西可就更有用了
-They're explosives, aren't they?  -Yes.
-那是炸药 对吗?  -是的
Explosives and detonators.
炸药和导火索
It seems almost providential.
似乎天意如此
Why? What are you going to use them for?
为什么? 你要拿它们做什么?
The Time Lord gave me three options.
时间领主给了我三种选择
There's only one still open.
现在只剩一种可行了
-Genocide.  -Genocide?
-种族灭绝  -种族灭绝?
Yes. I'm going to kill everything in the incubation room.
是的 我要把培育室里的那些生物都消灭
I'm going to destroy the Daleks forever.
我要使Dalek永远灭绝
Where is Davros?
Davros在哪里?
-You said that Davros had agreed to meet us here.
-He'll be here.
-你说过Davros同意在这里见我们  -他会来的
You have something to say to me?
你们有话要对我说?
Davros, we wish to make our views plain to you
concerning our work here.
Davros 我们想要向你清楚地表明 我们对于你的实验的看法
With what authority do you speak?
With whose backing?
你说这话是以什么身份? 是谁怂恿的?
We speak for virtually all the Elite
scientific corps and many of the military.
事实上 我们代表几乎全部精英小组科学部成员
We represent the majority.
我们代表着大多数
Very well. Continue.
非常好 继续说
Nobody disputes that in the past,
毋庸置疑 过去在你的领导下
under your guidance, we've made
incredible progress in many fields of science.
我们在许多科学领域得到了惊人发展
You did not come here to flatter me.
You came to offer an ultimatum.
你不是来奉承我的 你是来给我下最后通牒的
Confine yourself to the terms of that ultimatum.
直说最后通牒那部分吧
Very well.
很好
The initial concept of the Dalek
Dalek的最初概念
was to build a life support system
and a travel machine
是为我们种族终将进化成为的生物
for the creature that we know
our race will ultimately evolve into.
建立生命维持系统和代步机器
You disapprove of that?
你不同意?
No, but we believe that concept
has been perverted.
不是 我们认为这个概念已被歪曲了
You have tampered
with the genetic structuring of the creature
你篡改了这些生物的基因构造
to create a ruthless power for evil.
以创造一种邪恶残忍的力量
We cannot permit this to continue.
我们不能任由它继续下去
Then what do you suggest?
那你有什么建议
All work on Dalek projects is to cease immediately.
Dalek计划的所有工作立刻终止
The creatures that have been conditioned
and programmed are to be destroyed.
已被处理和编程过的生物
If these terms are met, we will then be proud
如果能满足这些条件 我们仍会自豪地
to work under your guidance
on the rebuilding of our society.
接受你的领导 重建这个社会
And if I refuse?
如果我拒绝呢
If you refuse, you will be placed under arrest.
如果你拒绝 我们会拘捕你
The Daleks will be destroyed
and our work here will then continue
Dalek会被销毁 我们在这儿的工作会继续
under a new, democratically elected leader.
由一个民主选举产生的领导带领我们
Have you finished?
你说完了吗
Well?
你的意思是?
You might at least do me the courtesy
of giving me time to consider.
你至少应该有点礼貌 给我点时间思考一下
(SQUEAKING)
The Daleks are in there.
那些Dalek在里面
The flesh and blood part of them.
血肉之躯那部分
Indeed they are flesh and blood.
其实也只是血肉之躯
Some of them can move about.
其中一些还能活动
Well, how do I see?
我怎么才能看看?
Press the button.
按一下按钮
-Here we go.  -Harry.
-来吧   -Harry
You're not going in there, are you?
你不是要进去吧?
They're harmless enough, I think. Just unpleasant.
我想它们应该不怎么危险 只是让人不舒服
-You don't want me to come in, do you, Doctor?
-There's no need, Harry.
-博士 你不会想让我也进去吧  -没必要 Harry
It just remains to put the charges
where they'll do the most damage.
只需要把炸药放在能造成最大破坏的位置上
It shouldn't take me more than a couple of minutes.
这应该花不了几分钟
I have made my decision.
我已经决定了
I accept your ultimatum.
我接受你们的最后通牒
-On one condition.  -Go on.
-但有一个条件  -你说
That you allow me to speak to a full meeting
of the Elite, both scientific and military.
让我在精英小组全体成员面前发言 科学部和军事部都要参加
Anyone you elect may speak against me.
你们选举的人可以与我辩论
When this is done, a vote will be taken.
一切完成后 进行一次投票
I will abide by the decision of the majority.
我会服从多数人的决定
You already know the decision of the majority.
You will lose, Davros.
你已经知道多数人的决定了 你会输的 Davros
With such confidence,
you can hardly deny my request.
有这样的自信 你应该不会拒绝我的请求
It was you who introduced the word ''democracy''.
是你说要讲"民主"的
Do we accept his proposition?
我们要接受他的提议吗
Very well, it's agreed.
好 我们同意
The meeting will take place in one hour from now.
Arrange it.
会议在一小时后召开 安排一下
You may go.
你们可以走了
Ours is the victory, Nyder. We have won.
我们才是胜者 Nyder 我们赢了
What's taking him so long?
他怎么弄了那么久?
It's a very difficult operation, Sarah.
Still, he should have finished by now.
因为操作很精细 Sarah 不过就算如此 他现在也该弄完了
Doctor?
博士
Doctor, are you all right?
博士 你没事吧
Sarah!
Get it off!
把它弄下来
Got it.
好了
Doctor!
博士
What are you waiting for?
你还在等什么
Just touch these two strands together
只要把这两根线头相碰
and the Daleks are finished.
Dalek就终结了
Have I that right?
我有这个权利吗
To destroy the Daleks? You can't doubt it.
去毁灭Dalek吗 毫无疑问
Well, I do.
我不确定
You see, some things could be better with the Daleks.
瞧 有些事情会因为Dalek存在而变得更好
Many future worlds will become allies
just because of their fear of the Daleks.
未来的许多世界会结成同盟 就是因为出于对Dalek的恐惧
But it isn't like that.
但事情不能这样看
But the final responsibility is mine, and mine alone.
可最终责任要我承担 我独自一人承担
Listen, if someone who knew the future
听着 如果一个知晓未来的人
pointed out a child to you
and told you that that child
指着一个孩子 告诉你 这个孩子
would grow up totally evil,
长大后会变得十分邪恶
to be a ruthless dictator
who would destroy millions of lives,
会变成一个残暴的独裁者 杀掉成百万的人
could you then kill that child?
你下得了手杀掉这个小孩吗
We're talking about the Daleks.
The most evil creatures ever invented.
但这可是Dalek 有史以来最邪恶的生物
You must destroy them. You must complete
your mission for the Time Lords.
你必须毁掉他们 你必须为时间领主完成这个使命
Do I have the right?
我有这个权利吗
Simply touch one wire against the other and that's it.
只不过把这两根线连在一起
The Daleks cease to exist.
Dalek将不复存在
Hundreds of millions of people,
数亿条生命
thousands of generations
can live without fear, in peace,
千万个世代 可以免于恐惧 宁静度日
and never even know the word ''Dalek''.
甚至绝不会知道Dalek这个词语
Then why wait?
所以还等什么呢
If it was a disease or some sort of bacteria
you were destroying, you wouldn't hesitate.
如果你要消灭的是一种疾病或某种细菌 你不会犹豫不决
But if I kill, wipe out a whole intelligent life form,
可如果我动手 将一种智慧生命彻底屠灭
then I become like them.
我就变得跟他们一样了
I'd be no better than the Daleks.
我岂不是无异于Dalek
SARAH: Think of all the suffering
there'll be if you don't do it.
如果你不这么做 想想所有即将来临的苦难吧
GHARMAN: Doctor!
博士
Doctor, I've been looking everywhere for you.
博士 我在到处找你
Davros has agreed to our terms.
Davros同意了我们的条件
-He submitted?
-He did. But he asked only one thing.
-他屈服了?  -是的 但他提出一个条件
That he might be allowed to address a meeting
of all the Elite, scientific and military.
那就是他要在大会上发言 整个精英小组 科学部和军事部全体参会
He's going to put a case?
他要提出提案吗
Yes, but a vote will be taken.
It's a foregone conclusion.
是的 但是要进行投票 结果可以预见
There will be a complete landslide
against any further development of the Daleks.
肯定会有一边倒的绝对优势 反对Dalek任何进一步的发展
We've won.
我们已经赢了
I'm grateful to you, Gharman.
非常感激你 Gharman
More grateful than I can tell you.
我对你的感激简直是无以言表
Everybody is here, Davros.
所有人都到齐了 Davros
The issues are simple and clear cut.
问题十分简单明了
I have given my life's work
to the survival of our race.
我毕生精力都奉献于我们种族的生存
The travel machine I designed, the Dalek
我设计的行动机器 Dalek
will give the creature into which we will mutate
是保证我们进化之后
its only possibility of continued existence.
继续生存的唯一可能
But you have deviated from that intention.
你已经偏离了原本的意图
You have introduced genetic changes
that will alter the mutation into
你引入的基因改变 会将变异体改造成
a creature without morals and without ethics.
毫无伦理道德感的怪物
One race must survive all others.
诸多种族中只有一个能生存下来
And to do this, it must dominate.
为了达到这个目的 这个种族必须主宰一切
Ruthlessly.
毫不留情
Now I intend that
when all the bickering and battling is over,
我的目标是 当一切争吵和战斗都结束的时候
the supreme victor shall be our race,
最终的胜者将是我们种族
the Daleks.
Dalek
At this very moment,
此时此刻
the production lines stand ready,
totally automated, fully programmed.
生产线已经准备好 全自动化 全程序化
The Daleks are no longer dependent on us.
Dalek将不再依赖于我们
The machinery is ready.
They are a power in their own right.
机器已准备就绪 他们是一支自主的力量
If any one of you would destroy
everything that we have ever achieved,
如果你们任何一位想要摧毁 我们所取得的一切成果
then here...
那么 这儿
is a destruct button.
是一枚自毁按钮
Press it and you will destroy this bunker
and everything in it.
按下它 这个掩体和里面的一切都会被摧毁
You are men without courage.
一群懦夫
You have lost your right to survive.
你们已失去了生存的权利
You have heard Davros' case.
你们都听到Davros说的了
What he has not made clear
is that there is another way.
他有一点没讲清楚 那就是还有一个办法
There is no other way.
没有其他办法
Production of the Dalek can continue.
Dalek的制造可以继续
We can destroy the genetically conditioned creatures
我们可以毁灭基因改造过的生物
and allow the mutation to follow its own course.
任由基因自主演变
Our race will survive if it deserves to survive.
如果我们的种族值得生存下来的话 就不会灭亡
But let it have all the strengths
and weaknesses that we have,
但让它兼具我们的优势和缺陷
compassion and hate.
怜悯和仇恨
Let it do good things and evil.
让它善恶并存
But we cannot let it become
an unfeeling, heartless machine.
但不能让它变成没有感觉没有心的机器
That is our choice. Now...
这是我们的选择 现在
we must decide.
我们必须作出决定
-We've got to find that time ring.
-SARAH: Doctor.
-我们得找到时间手环  -博士
Good girl, Sarah.
好姑娘 Sarah
Now all we need is the tape recorder.
So keep an eye on Nyder.
现在我们只要找到录音机了 盯着点Nyder
You've heard our cases.
你们已经听完了我们的提案
I will give you two minutes to decide.
我给你们两分钟的时间做决定
Then you must answer not only to me,
but to the future.
你们不只是给我也是给未来一个答复
You've had ample time to decide.
你们已经有充足的时间来决定了
Those who would remain loyal to me
and to the future of our race,
依旧忠于我 也忠于我们种族的未来的
move forward and stand at my side.
向前走 站到我这边
Now, I wonder where Nyder is going
at such a crucial moment.
我倒想知道 Nyder在这么关键的时刻要去哪
-I think we ought to find out.
-So do I.
-我想我们得弄清楚  -我也这么想
Let's go.
走吧
Right, bring out the explosives.
好了 把炸药拿出来
Now, lay the charges on each of these main carriers.
在每个主承重梁上放炸药
One charge for each beam should be enough.
每根横梁一个炸药应该就够了
Now, where are you going in such a hurry?
你这么着急是要去哪啊
Davros is lost. I am getting away while I can.
Davros输了 我要趁还能跑赶快离开
Oh.
哦
Somehow that just doesn't ring true.
不知道为什么听着不像是真的
Why didn't you just join the other side?
你怎么不直接投靠另一边啊
Now, that's a good question.
Do you have a good answer?
问得好 你能答得漂亮吗
Evidently not.
显然不能
Well, then let's try something else.
That tape recorder you took. Where is it?
那我们问点别的吧 你拿走的录音机 它在哪
It's put away in a safe in Davros' office.
保存在Davros办公室的一个保险柜里
-Shall we go and see?
-Down here.
-我们要不要去看看  -从这走
Are you quite sure
this is the only way into the bunker?
你确定这是进入掩体的唯一路线?
Well, the only other way was from the Kaled dome
唯一的替代路线是从Kaled穹顶走
and your war rocket caved that in.
It can never be cleared.
你们的火箭把它炸塌了 无法清理出道路
If we do the same here, we'll entomb
the Daleks and those who created them.
如果在这里再来一次 我们就能埋葬Dalek和创造了他们的人
But Sarah and the Doctor are inside.
You'll give them a chance to get clear, won't you?
但是Sarah和博士还在里面 你会给他们机会逃出来的 对吧
I must blow the roof as soon as
the charges are laid. I can't delay.
我必须在炸药放置好以后立即炸塌屋顶 不能拖延
If the Daleks find out what we are doing and attack,
如果Dalek察觉我们的动作 发动攻击
I don't have enough men or arms to stand them off.
我没有足够的人手或是武器来抵御他们
-How long?
-Thirty minutes, perhaps less.
-多久  -三十分钟 也许更短
-Then I must get inside and try and warn them.
-That's up to you.
-那我必须进去提醒他们  -你自己作决定
But you must understand,
if you're not back, I must go on.
不过你要明白 如果你没回来 我还是要继续
-You'll die in there with them.
-I understand.
-你会和他们一起死在里面  -我明白
I'll give you what time I can.
我尽可能给你时间
Right.
好
Thank you.
谢谢你
Now, let's destroy it.
现在 让我们来毁掉它
-How about this?  -How very apt.
-这个怎么样  -再合适不过了
A Dalek gun.
一把Dalek枪
There.
好了
He's not important.
他不重要
We've got the time ring, we've destroyed
the tape and Davros' power is broken.
我们拿到了时间手环
What about the Daleks that are already operational?
那些已经投入运行的Dalek怎么办
Oh, I think we can leave Gharman to destroy them.
我们大可把他们留给Gharman去摧毁
-Why is it going on so long?  -Who knows?
-会议怎么进行了这么久  -谁知道呢
It's out of character for Davros
to submit quite so easily.
那么轻易地屈服可不是Davros的性格
This is your last chance. Move to join me now.
这是你们最后的机会了 过来站在我这边
Or suffer the consequences.
否则后果自负
Why don't you just accept the fact
that you have lost? It's over for you, Davros.
你怎么就不能接受现实 你输了 你已经完了 Davros
Do you believe that I would let a lifetime's work
你真的天真地以为我会把毕生的心血
be ended by the will of spineless fools like you?
葬送在你们这些没骨气的蠢货身上?
You have won nothing.
你们根本没有赢
I allowed this charade to be played out
for one reason only.
我任由这出戏上演 只为一个原因
To find those men who were truly loyal to me
就是找出那些真正忠于我的人
and to discover those who would betray me!
揭发出那些会背叛我的人
We...
我们...
I will go on!
我必将继续
You are insane, Davros.
你真是疯了 Davros
Exterminate!
消灭
Stop them, Davros. You must stop them.
住手 Davros 让他们住手
-That's the last one in position.
-Right. Prepare to detonate.
-最后一个也安放好了  -好的 准备引爆
The automated Dalek production line
has been started.
自动化的Dalek生产线已启动
I gave no such order. Who did?
我没下过这样的命令  谁下的
DALEK: I gave the command.
我下的命令
You will perform no function
unless ordered by me.
除非我下令 否则你不能做出任何行动
You will obey only my commands.
你只能服从我的命令
The production line is to be halted immediately.
生产线必须立即停止
You heard my order. Obey!
你听见我的命令了  听令
Obey!
听令
I created you! I am the master, not you!
我创造了你们 主人是我 不是你们
I. I. I!
是我 是我 是我
-Nyder.  -Yes, Davros.
-Nyder  -是 Davros
Production will continue.
生产不能停止
DALEK: Our programming does not permit us
我们的内置程序不认可
to acknowledge that any creature
is superior to the Daleks.
其它任何生物优于Dalek
You cannot exist without me.
没有我 你们就不会存在
All inferior creatures are to be considered
所有的劣等生物都被视作
the enemy of the Daleksand destroyed.
Dalek的敌人 都要被消灭
No, wait!
不 等等
Exterminate!
消灭
For the last time, I am your creator!
最后再说一遍 我是你们的创造者
You must, you will obey me!
你们必须 你们要服从我
We obey no one.
我们不服从任何人
We are the superior beings.
我们是至高无上的存在
Exterminate!
消灭
(DAVROS SCREAMING)
Main exit blocked by explosion
主入口因爆炸
for a length of at least 1,000 yards.
阻塞了至少1000码
We are entombed, but we live on.
我们被埋入地下 但我们会活下去
This is only the beginning.
这只是开始
We will prepare. We will grow stronger.
我们将做好准备 我们会更加强大
When the time is right, we will emerge
等时机成熟 我们会东山再起
and take our rightful place
夺回我们应有的地位
as the supreme powe of the universe!
成为宇宙中至高无上的强权者
Failed? No, not really.
失败了? 不 不算
DOCTOR: You see, I know
你看 尽管我知道
that although the Daleks will create
havoc and destruction for millions of years,
Dalek在数百万年里 将会带来浩劫与毁灭
I know also that out of their evil
我也知道 他们的邪恶
must come something good.
一定也伴随着一些善果
(SARAH GRUNTS)
Thank heaven for that. We've made it.
-Haven't we?  -Of course we've made it.
Did you think we wouldn't?
Well, in these past few weeks, yes.
-Quite frequently.  -There is really nothing
that could go wrong with the time ring,
except the molecular short circuit.
-Doctor.  -Yes?
The Tardis isn't here.
Well, it probably hasn't arrived yet.
We're a little early.
Hasn't arrived yet?
No, you see, the Tardis is drifting back
through time, Harry.
We'll just have to wait for it to turn up.
(CHUCKLES)
I say, Doctor, did you want this ring thing?
-What, that?  -Yes.
-No.  -Oh, well, I'd rather like to have it.
-Well, you take good care of it, Harry.
-Of course I will. Thank you.
(GASPS)
You knew that was gonna happen, didn't you?
-He's dead. Been dead some time.  -How long?
A week or two, I'd say.
There's very little sign of putrefaction though.
Sterile atmosphere.
Yes, exactly, and no sign of injury.
Nothing to indicate the cause of death.
Well, he was just sitting against
the door as though he'd collapsed.
He wouldn't have been there for two weeks unless...
Unless what?
Unless there was something seriously wrong here.
Come on.
基于ClassicWho 字幕组字幕文件裁剪
翻译   YVONNE 薛音 梦泽小猪 秉秉
校对   Knight.S 风过柳下 张小抽
时间轴   Miss荣
纠错   Rogner  Knight.S 风过柳下 恣肆~